TheChaosLegion
I want to shine on you, and always like that dazzling sun.
I will defend you from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
If only our hearts could connect, I could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time, and I know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day, I'll be there for you.
I hope I can watch over you like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
～♪
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
（シュガ）この辺りのはずだが…
It should be somewhere
around here.
急がねば
昨日の大雨で消えた毒霧が―
If I don't hurry, the poison mist that
yesterday's downpour cleared away...
...will return to the valley floor.
再び谷底を満たしてしまう
Highness, I shall return
with proof that Prince Chagum...
殿下 チャグム皇子の生きている証し
必ずや持ち帰ります！
...is still alive without fail!
Episode 16
With All One's Heart
（帝(みかど)）許せ…
Forgive me.
今は まだ この事実を
外に漏らすことはできんのだ
For the time being, we can't let anyone
outside the palace know of his death.
When the time is right, I promise
that the entire country will mourn him.
しかるべき時が来たら
必ずや国を挙げて弔おう
Until then, please endure your grief.
それまでは辛抱してくれ
（聖導師(せいどうし)のため息）
（聖導師）帝がおられぬと
人々の心も千々(ちぢ)に乱れる
Without the mikado, everyone
is distracted and unfocused.
If this state of affairs continues,
the government will cease to function.
このままでは
政(まつりごと)が立ち行かなくなってしまう
わずかに残された望みは…
And our one faint
glimmer of hope is...
なぜ そなたたちが ここに
What are you men doing here?
（ジン）無人を手なずけ
碑文ノ間(ひぶんのま)に出入りしていたこと―
The master star reader
has known all along...
...that you won the trust of the vessels
and entered the chamber of epitaphs.
聖導師様は とうにお気付きだ！
（モン）我らは
聖導師様の命により ここに参った
We are here on orders of
the master star reader.
シュガ様が この地に赴いたのは―
I assume that you
have come here...
...because you believe that
Prince Chagum is alive.
チャグム皇子が生きておられると
考えてのことだと察するが―
But just how much faith do
you have in your deductions?
その推理 どこまで自信がおありか
In the course of reading the epitaphs,
my hope changed to certainty.
碑文を読み 願望が確信に変わった
もし その確信とやらが
誤りであったならば―
If this so-called certainty of yours
should prove to be mistaken...
...I must warn you that
you will die with this man...
あなた様は
あの者とともに むくろとなり―
...and your corpses will be
lost forever in this valley.
谷底に消えるものと
覚悟していただきたい！
毒霧が引いている…
The poison mist has receded.
If only I had gone down
to the valley floor that day...
あのとき すぐに
谷底に降りていればな…
あったのは
黒蝗馬(こっこうば)の死骸と衣装のみ
All I found there was the corpse of
their Kokkou stallion and their clothing.
皇子と女用心棒の死体は なかった
There was no sign of the corpses
of the prince and the bodyguard.
If I hadn't stopped you,
we would have...
（ゼン）
私がお止めせねば 今頃は…
There was enough poison mist
that day to kill even me.
あのときは 俺でも
生きて帰れぬほどの 毒霧が出ていた
正しい判断だ
You made the correct decision.
これで 皇子の
生存の確率は高まった
The odds of the prince being
alive are now much higher.
あとは どうやって
皇子を見つけ出すか…
The question now
is how to find him...
その手段 考えておられるのか？
Have you given the
matter any thought?
無論だ
Of course.
（モン）急ぎ 宮に戻るぞ
We'll make haste
back to the palace.
まずは 帝と聖導師様に
このことを ご報告せねばならん
We must first report this to the
mikado and the master star reader.
Prince Sagum will be
overjoyed at this news as well.
サグム殿下も
さぞ お喜びになるだろう
Master Shuga...
（モン）シュガ様
心してお聞きください
Brace yourself for what
I am about to tell you.
（シュガ）
あのとき せめて ひと言―
If only I had told him that Prince Chagum
was alive when I had the chance...
“チャグム皇子は生きておられる”と
そう伝えられていたら…
Master Star Reader,
as you are already aware...
聖導師様
すでにご存じのとおり
私は秘倉に忍び入り―
...I have been infiltrating the secret
repository and reading the epitaphs.
一人 碑文を
読み進めてまいりました
そして ある重大な事実を
見いだしたのです
And in doing so, I discovered
a fact of utmost importance.
The legends set down in the official history
regarding the founding of Shin-Yogo...
建国正史(けんこくせいし)に語られる
我が新ヨゴ皇国建国の言い伝えに―
大きな誤りがあったことを
...contain grave errors.
The official history
is nothing but a story...
（シュガ）建国正史は
この国の民を統べるために―
...a fabrication designed
to control the country.
作り上げられた 偽りの物語
そして水妖(すいよう)とは 本来 雲を吐き
この地に恵みをもたらす―
And the water demon was in fact
a water spirit that spews forth clouds...
...bringing bounty to our land.
水の精霊だったのです
うーむ…
にわかには信じられん話だが…
I find your story difficult to believe.
先住民であったヤクーたちは―
Long before the arrival of
Emperor Torugaru, our founding father...
...the Yakoo, the original
inhabitants of this land...
聖祖トルガル帝が
この地に降り立つ以前から―
...were aware of the existence of
Nayug, a world other than our own.
この世とは別の世 ナユグの
存在に気づいており―
その はざまにおりし精霊の
もたらす恵みのあることを―
They understood that
our bounty is caused by...
...a spirit that
dwells between worlds.
理解していたのです
Kainan Nanai sensed
this as a threat.
そのことに脅威を感じた
カイナン･ナナイは―
By creating a new
myth for the public...
表向き 別の神話をねつ造することで
ヤクーの伝承を絶やし―
...he eradicated the
Yakoo's oral traditions...
...and laid the foundation
for the Shin-Yogo Empire.
我らが新ヨゴ皇国の礎を
築いてくださった
However, aware of the danger
of letting the fateful day arrive...
ですが 誤った伝承を伝えたまま
きたるべき日が訪れては困ると―
...having armed us only
with the incorrect oral history...
碑文ノ間を作り
我らに真実を託したのです
He built the epitaph chamber
in order to entrust us with the truth.
On one of those stone tablets kept
underground, the following was inscribed:
あの地下の石碑の一文に
こう うたわれた箇所がございました
“星読みの職務に
就きし者たちは―”
"Those who serve as star readers must
read and decipher what is written here..."
“100年ごとに起こりうるであろう
天災に備え―”
"...to prepare for the natural disaster
which will come every hundred years..."
"...passing down the knowledge
to each successive generation."
“ここに記する文言を解読し
絶えず後世に語り継ぐべし”と
今回の出来事は まさに
聖導師様が私に語られたとおり―
What is happening now is
exactly as you said, Master.
政に気を取られすぎた 我ら星読みの
怠慢が招いた有事にございます
We brought this emergency
down on ourselves...
...as the result of us star readers
becoming preoccupied with politics!
その証拠に
碑文の示す事柄を追った結果―
As proof of this, by studying
the events set forth in the epitaphs...
...I am now almost certain
that Prince Chagum is still alive.
チャグム皇子の存命を
ほぼ確認することができたのです
皇子は今も
精霊の卵を宿したまま―
The prince still carries
the spirit's egg within him...
...and he is living somewhere
in Kosenkyo as we speak!
この光扇京(こうせんきょう)のどこかで
暮らしております！
では 仮に皇子に宿りしつきものが
水をもたらす精霊だとして―
If the being inside the prince is
indeed a spirit that creates water...
...how do you explain the sign of
the great drought not disappearing?
いまだ晴れぬ乾ノ相(かわきのそう)に関しては
なんとする？
このたびの乾ノ相は 水の精霊の
生まれ変わりに際し起こる―
The sign of the drought
that we see now is...
...a preordained sign that occurs
when the spirit is about to be reborn.
あらかじめ定められた
相にございます
Had the prince been assassinated,
not only would there have been no rain...
もし あのとき
皇子を暗殺していたら―
昨日の豪雨はもとより
もはや この地に二度と―
...but I expect these lands would
never have had another drop of water.
水の恵みは
もたらされなかったことでしょう
（帝）シュガよ
（シュガ）はっ…
Shuga.
（帝）その話 誠であろうな？
Is what you just said true?
はい 私は
そう確信しております
Yes. I am convinced of it.
You are certain that
Chagum is alive, then?
では チャグムは 間違いなく
生きておるというのだな？
はい
Yes.
まだ そのお姿を
じかに拝見してはおりませぬが―
Although I have not seen him with
my own eyes, there can be no doubt.
間違いないかと
I see...
そうか…
もし 私めに チャグム皇子捜索の
権限をいただけたなら―
If I were to be given command
of the search for Prince Chagum...
...I shall find him
in a matter of days!
数日の後に
皇子を見つけ出してまいります
Mikado...
帝…
私は 自身で思っていた以上に―
It would appear that
I was even more obsessed...
政に うつつを
抜かしていたようでございます
...with political matters
than I realized.
今の私にできることは
１つしかございません
There is but one thing
that I can do now.
このシュガめに チャグム皇子捜索に
関わる全権をお与えください
Sire, please grant Shuga full command
over the search for Chagum.
I beg of you on his behalf. Please...
私からも お願い申し上げます
何とぞ…
Very well. Do as you see fit.
分かった
思うようにするがよい
Thank you, Majesty.
（聖導師）ありがとうございます
Sire, there is something that I must
ask to borrow to carry out the search.
皇子捜索に際し １つ
お借りしたいものがございます
何を借りたいと申すのじゃ
What is it that you wish the use of?
（サヤ）あっ
はい お茶
Here, have some tea.
（トーヤ）おっ ありがとう
Oh, thanks.
（タンダ）
ずいぶん繁盛しているようだな
Looks like business is booming.
Welcome to...
（サヤ）いらっしゃいまし！
Oh, it's you, Tanda.
（トーヤ）何だ タンダか
Is that any way to welcome me?
I'm here as a customer today.
（タンダ）何だは ないだろう
今日は客として来たんだぞ
I'd like you to deliver these
goods to this address here.
これらの品を…
ここに届けておいてほしいんだ
できれば今日か あす中に
If at all possible, today
or tomorrow. Can you do it?
できるかな？
Who do you think you're talking to?
I'm the best errand runner in this city.
誰にものを言ってるんだよ
俺は この街一番の
頼まれ屋だぜ？
そうだったな
じゃあ問題ない
Right, I forgot.
There won't be any problems, then.
よろしくな
I'll leave you to it.
（モン）シュガ様
（シュガ）あっ…
Master Shuga.
（モン）
そろそろ仕掛けようと思いますが
I would like to launch our plan soon.
機は お前たちに任せる
Your men may start whenever
you think the timing is right.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
I can gather these
supplies for you today...
（トーヤ）今日中に用意できるけど
その支度からすると―
...but from the looks of this order,
is Balsa planning another long trip?
ねえさん どこか遠出する気かな？
（タンダ）
さあ そいつはどうかな
Hm, I don't know about that.
あっ そういうことなら
うまく 分からないように届けるよ
In that case, I'll make sure that
no one knows about the delivery.
Here's the money she
told me to give to you.
これは あいつから預かった代金だ
そいつは受け取れねえよ！
We can't take Balsa's money!
It's thanks to her that Saya
and I have our own shop now.
こうやって 俺とサヤが店を持てたのは
ねえさんのおかげなんだ
Admittedly, she did tell us
that we shouldn't use it yet...
本当は まだ使っちゃいけないって
言われてたのに…
So let us do something to repay her.
だから 少しぐらい
俺たちにも恩返しさせてくれよ
そうか 分かった
Okay. I understand.
じゃあ そう伝えておくよ
I'll tell her that.
That's more like it.
（トーヤ）そう来なくっちゃ
（タンダ）ハハッ
Okay, I'm counting on you.
じゃ 頼んだぞ
Sure thing! Leave everything to me!
（トーヤ）あいよ 任せとけって
毎度！
Pleasure doing business with you!
あれ？ 棟りょう！
Hey, Chief! What brings
you here at this hour?
今日はどうしたんです？
こんな時間に
実は さるお屋敷で
大きな改築を頼まれてな
Well, we've been hired to do
a major renovation on a mansion.
I'm trying to get everything ready.
（戸の開閉音）
（ゼン）今日はその準備に追われている
ひのきを
大量に買い付けたいんだが―
I want to buy a lot of cypress wood.
As I recall, you also deal in lumber, right?
確か お前のところは
木材も扱えたな？
You bet we do!
（トーヤ）もちろんですよ！
だてに頼まれ屋の看板
上げてるわけじゃありませんからね！
That "Errand Runner" sign isn't
just there for show, you know!
まっ 話は中で
Come on, let's discuss
the details inside.
I must say, I'm amazed.
しかし驚かされる
５日で 報告にあった頼まれ屋を
見つけ出し―
In five days, you found the errand
runner mentioned in the reports...
３日で あそこまで
警戒心を解くとは…
...and in three days, you've
managed to gain his complete trust.
It takes more to be a Hunter
than being a skilled warrior.
狩人は 腕の立つ武人であれば
務まるというわけではありません
Rather, our true strength
is intelligence-gathering.
諜報こそが むしろ我らの本懐
そうだったな
Yes, of course.
We now know that the bodyguard...
しかし あの女用心棒がチャグム皇子と
光扇京で暮らすためには―
...cannot live in Kosenkyo
with Prince Chagum...
頼まれ屋の存在が欠かせぬ
ということは分かったが―
...without the assistance
of the errand runner.
But what next?
次はどうする？
I doubt that she will
come here in person.
じかに姿を現すとは思えんが
Stand back and watch,
and all will be resolved soon.
黙って見ていてくだされば
すぐに片はつきます
（トーヤ）期日が７日後ってんなら
間に合わせますよ？
If the deadline is in seven days,
I'll be able to deliver it in time.
Will this be enough for the deposit?
手付けには これで足りるか？
十分です ありがとうございます
More than enough! Thanks a lot.
ちょっと待っててください
手形切りますんで
Wait here a moment.
I'll go make out your bill.
動いた
He's on the move.
どうぞ
（ゼン）うむ
Here you are.
（トーヤ）おっと
Oops!
Sorry to keep you waiting.
Here's your bill.
お待たせしました
手形にございます
All right, then. I'll deliver the items
you requested in seven days' time.
それでは ７日後に 必ず
ご所望の品をお届けしますんで
うむ 任せたぞ
I'm counting on you.
ご苦労だった
Well done.
You memorized everything
in such a short time?
あの短時間に
全てを暗記したというのか…？
Judging from the distance, I'd estimate
two days each way if we take our time.
（バルサ）この距離だと
ゆっくり見積もって 片道２日
正味５日ってとこか
Say, five days total.
ちょっと心もとないね…
I'm not sure this will last...
（チャグム）うーん…
（バルサ）チャグム
Chagum, we're going
to Ogi no Shimo.
（チャグム）ん？
（バルサ）扇(おうぎ)の下(しも)まで出かけるよ
旅の資金も調達したいし―
I want to pick up money for the trip...
...and I'll get you some
leggings and a karru.
お前の脚半と
カッルも買ってやろう
All right.
分かった
Rai. Hyok.
ライ ヒョク
（ライ･ヒョク）はっ
Rai. Hyok.
Sir.
タガ スン
（タガ･スン）はっ！
Taga. Sune.
Sir.
Split into two-man teams and check
each of these locations in order.
この場所を ２人組で順番に当たれ
（一同）はっ
Sir!
When you locate the
spear-wielder's hideout...
短槍(たんそう)使いの隠れ家を見つけたら―
必ず １人を見張りに残し
すぐ連絡しろ
...make certain you leave one man as
a lookout and report back immediately.
我ら全員で 一斉に奇襲をかける
We'll launch a surprise
attack as a team.
単独で仕掛けることは
絶対に許さん
Under no circumstances is
anyone to engage her alone.
今度こそ確実にしとめるぞ
（一同）はっ！
We will kill her for certain this time.
Sir!
Everyone else, remain here and
keep watch on the errand runner.
あとの者は ここに残り
頼まれ屋を見張る
I have nothing to add.
私からは 何も言うことはない
I will leave the searching
to you, but I ask that you...
あとは任せるが 皇子奪還の際には
必ず私を同行させてくれ
...allow me to accompany you
when you recover the prince.
When you tried to assassinate him,
the prince got a look at your faces.
お前たちは 暗殺の際
皇子に顔を見られている
If I am not there,
he will be frightened.
私がいなければ
チャグム皇子も恐れるだろうからな
皇子の身を案じているのは
あなた様だけではござらん
You are not the only one who
is concerned about His Highness.
That's enough, Jin.
やめろ ジン
承知いたしました
Understood. But what
about you, Master Shuga?
して シュガ様は
どうされますかな？
短槍使いの隠れ家は 今日にも
見つかるやもしれませぬが―
We might locate the
spear-wielder's hideout today...
３日後になるやも…
...or it might be
three days from now.
As for me, I will
return to the palace...
（シュガ）
私は 一度宮に戻り―
...and prepare for further
reading of the epitaphs.
碑文を さらに読み進める
手はずを整える
As soon as Prince Chagum arrives,
I must stage his miraculous return...
チャグム皇子が戻りしだい
皇子の奇跡の生還を演出し―
いまだ その死を 公にして
差し上げることすらかなわぬ―
...and we must also provide
a state funeral for Prince Sagum...
...whose death we have not yet
been able to disclose to the public.
サグム殿下の国葬も 同時に
執り行わなければならんからな
To do so, a cover story
will be necessary.
そのための理由づけが必要となる
If circumstances warrant it, we may
have to rewrite the official history itself.
場合によっては 建国正史すら
書き換えねばならんのだ
Understood. We will
be sure to send for you.
分かりました
必ずお呼びいたします
頼んだぞ
I'm counting on you.
How much farther is it?
どこまで行くんだ？
（バルサ）行けば分かるさ
You'll understand
when we get there.
頼まれ屋が店を空けるぞ
The errand runner
is leaving his store.
（サヤ）いってらっしゃい
（トーヤ）ああ
See you later.
Sure.
The boy has never left his shop
to deliver goods himself.
（モン）小僧自らが荷を担いで
店を空けるのは 初めてのことだな
ユン！
（ユン）はっ
Yun!
Sir.
（モン）
ゼンは少し距離を置いて尾行しろ
Zen, you are to tail him at a distance.
Your face is known to him.
お前は 頼まれ屋に
顔を知られている
だが いざというときは
棟りょうを装い 情報を引き出せ
In case of emergency, however,
extract information as the "Chief."
Sir.
This is a...
（チャグム）ここは…
That's right, a graveyard.
Come with me.
（バルサ）そう お墓さ
ついてきな
It's this one if I recall correctly...
確か ここだったね…
あっ！ バルサ
Balsa, what are you doing?
You'll get into trouble!
何してるんだ？ 怒られるぞ
（チャグム）え？
（バルサ）家に置いとくのも―
It's too risky to
keep it in the house...
物騒だし いちいち
持って歩くのも面倒だからね
...and carrying it around
would be troublesome.
こうやって
あっちこっちに隠してあるのさ
I have it hidden in
various places, you see.
お金？
Money?
We've been able to live without
me working as a bodyguard...
今まで 用心棒稼業もせずに
暮らしてこられたのは―
こういう秘密があったのさ
...because of these secret hoards.
Ah, I see.
（チャグム）なるほど
“もずの はやにえ”のようなものか
Just like a wood shrike's stash.
ん？ はやにえ？
Wood shrike?
Ah, yes, just like that.
ああ そうかもな
うまい言葉 知ってんだな
You have a way with words.
えっへへへ…
It'll be quite a long journey
to reach Toumi village.
（バルサ）トウミ村までは
ちょっとした旅になる
Be ready to do a lot of walking.
結構歩くから覚悟しときな
With a new pair of leggings
and karru, I'll be fine.
（チャグム）新しい脚半と
カッルがあれば 大丈夫だよ！
I'm not so sure... I'm not going to
carry you on my back any more.
どうだかね
もう おんぶしてやらないよ
むっ 大丈夫だよ
I'll be fine!
（チャグム）うわっ！
（バルサ）ああ ごめん ごめん
Sorry about that.
Take this to buy yourself
some hekimooms or something.
これでヘキムームでも買ってきな
Really? Can I?
えっ いいの？
ああ あしたからは
しばらく食べられないからね
Sure. This will be your last
chance to eat them for a while.
うまく値切って
いっぱい買ってきな！
Haggle the vendor
for as many as you can.
わあ うん！
Right!
As I sat huddled and alone, holding back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like I was about to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were, at my side before I knew it.
It was none other than you who was there for me.
I keep wishing, "I want to be strong." I stumble and hurt myself again.
But because I have you to believe in, I can get back to my feet.
I simply want to tell my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs, again and again.
I call out to my precious loved one.
Is my voice reaching you?
In this world that always changes, human warmth never does.
I'm certain I sensed the presence of the one that I hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
Having fallen into the Hunters' trap...
...Toya risks his life
to rescue Balsa, but then...
Next time,
"The Water Mill Burns."
Episode 17
The Water Mill Burns
Forgive me, Toya.